Guide to the Arnold Ronnebeck Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Arnold Ronnebeck papers
1896-1952
1910-1947
YCAL MSS 692
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.84
(16 boxes) + 3 art, 1 broadside folder
The Arnold Ronnebeck papers contain correspondence, manuscripts, artwork, photographs, and printed and other materials documenting the life and career of the Prussian-born artist. Correspondence in the collection includes letters from other artists, family, and organizations, and includes letters from well-known modernist-era artists, such as George Grosz, Marsden Hartley, Wassily Kandinsky, Georgia O'Keeffe, and Alfred Stieglitz. Manuscripts include notebooks, journals Ronnebeck kept while in Paris from 1910 to 1912, and loose notes. Original artwork in the collection includes lithographs and busts of Hartley. Photographs include images of Ronnebeck's sculptures and the artwork of others, images of the artist at work and with other people, and images from the war years, 1914 through 1917, such as urban and rural landscapes, architectural sites of interest, and soldiers. Printed materials include art catalogs, ephemera, and clippings, and other materials include biographical information, personal papers, and childhood sketchbooks.
Ronnebeck, Arnold, 1885-1947
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Louise Ronnebeck, 1952-1972.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm available for portions of the collection.
Associated Materials
Arnold Ronnebeck and Louise Emerson Ronnebeck Papers, Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.
Arnold Ronnebeck (1885-1947)
Arnold Ronnebeck (1885-1947), born in Nassau, Germany (then Prussia), was a modernist sculptor and lithographer. Ronnebeck studied sculpture with Aristide Maillol and Émile-Antoine Bourdelle in Paris between 1907 and 1913 and emigrated to the United States in 1923. He is best known for his lithographs of New York City in the 1920s and depictions of western life in Colorado and New Mexico from the 1920s through 1940s. He settled in Denver, Colorado and worked as an art advisor to the Denver Art Museum from 1926 to 1931.
Biographical information taken from The Art of Arnold Ronnebeck <http://www.arnoldronnebeck.com/> accessed 17 January 2013.
Scope and Contents
The Arnold Ronnebeck papers contain correspondence, manuscripts, artwork, photographs, and printed and other materials documenting the career and life of the Prussian-born artist. Correspondence in the collection includes letters from other artists, family, and organizations, and includes letters from well-known modernist-era artists, such as George Grosz, Marsden Hartley, Wassily Kandinsky, Georgia O'Keeffe, and Alfred Stieglitz. Manuscripts include notebooks, journals Ronnebeck kept while in Paris from 1910 to 1912, and loose notes. Original artwork in the collection includes lithographs and busts of Hartley. Photographs include images of Ronnebeck's sculptures and the artwork of others, images of the artist at work and with other people, and images from the war years, 1914 through 1917, such as urban and rural landscapes, architectural sites of interest, and soldiers. Printed materials include art catalogs, ephemera, and clippings, and other materials include biographical information, personal papers, and childhood sketchbooks.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1915-1952. II. Manuscripts, 1900-1948. III. Artwork, 1913-1947. IV. Photographs, 1909-1923. V. Printed Materials, 1909-1948. VI. Other Materials, 1896-1938.
Artists -- France -- Paris; World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; Lithographers; Sculptors; Sculpture, Modern -- 20th Century; Lithographs; Photographic prints; Sculpture (visual work); Artists; Lithographers; Sculptors; Grosz, George, 1893-1959; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943; Kandinsky, Wassily, 1866-1944; O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1887-1986; Ronnebeck, Arnold, 1885-1947; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946
- Correspondence, 1915-1952; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence includes incoming letters from other artists, family, and organizations. Correspondents include George Grosz, Marsden Hartley, Wassily Kandinsky, Georgia O'Keeffe, Max Sidow, and Alfred Stieglitz.
  Dates listed below are circa dates.
  There are a small number of third-party letters addressed to Mrs. Ronnebeck dating from 1948 forward.
  - "A" general, 1917-1945, undated (Box 1)
  - American Artists Group, 1935-1946 (Box 1)
  - "B" general, 1927-1947 (Box 1)
  - Bear, Donald J., 1934 October 1 (Box 1)
  - Broadmoor Art Pottery and Tile Company, 1933-1941, undated (Box 1)
  - "C" general, 1927-1946, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Caproni Galleries, 1936-1944, undated (Box 1)
  - "D" general, 1927-1946, undated (Box 1)
  - Däubler, Theodor, 1921-1934, undated (Box 1)
    Includes photographs
  - "E-F" general, 1926-1946 (Box 1)
  - Frolich, Paul A., 1944, undated (Box 1)
  - "G" general, 1933-1946 (Box 1)
  - Grosz, George, 1930-1955; 5 (Box 2)
    Includes photographs and illustrations
  - "H" general, 1927-1944, undated (Box 2)
  - Hartley, Marsden, 1928-1946, undated (Box 2)
    Includes third-party correspondence, printed materials, and photographs
  - "I-K" general, 1928-1946 (Box 2)
  - Kandinsky, Wassily, 1925 February 13 (Box 2)
  - "L" general, 1924-1952 (Box 2)
  - Laboratory of Anthropology, 1928-1947, undated (Box 2)
  - "M-N" general, 1927-1943, undated (Box 3)
  - Matuschka, Franz Joseph, 1941-1944, undated (Box 3)
    Includes third-party correspondence
  - Matuschka, [George, Graf von?], 1920, undated (Box 3)
  - "O-R" general, 1927-1947, undated (Box 3)
  - O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1928, 1930 (Box 3)
  - Ronnebeck, Arnold (outgoing), 1920-1941, undated (Box 3)
  - Ronnebeck, R., 1929-1944, undated (Box 3)
  - "S-T" general, 1929-1948, undated (Box 3)
  - Sidow, Max, 1919-1927, undated; 3 (Box 3)
    Includes drafts of writings by Sidow
  - Stein, Gertrude, undated (Box 3)
    Includes clippings and drafts of writings
  - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1924-1946 (Box 3)
  - Sussmann, Toni, 1937-1945 (Box 4)
  - Thompson, John, undated (Box 4)
    Includes photograph
  - "U-Z" general, 1924-1946, undated (Box 4)
  - U.S. Treasury Dept., 1928-1939 (Box 4)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1915-1947, undated; 5 (Box 4)
    Includes clippings and other material
  - Empty binder, undated (Box 4)
- Notes and Notebooks, 1900-1948; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Series II. Notes and Notebooks contains bound notebooks and journals and loose notes, including three Paris journals dating from 1910 to 1912.
  - Notes and notebooks, 1929-1948, undated; 6 (Box 5)
  - Notes and notebooks, 1900-1945, undated; 6 (Box 6)
- Artwork, 1913-1947; Series III; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Series III. Artwork contains original lithographs and busts by Ronnebeck, including portraits of Marsden Hartley and himself.
  See Series VI. Other Materials for sketchbooks.
  - Lithographs, 1925-1934, undated (Box 7 (Broadside))
  - Portrait bust of Marsden Hartley, [circa 1913] (Box 8 (Art))
  - Portrait bust of Marsden Hartley, [1923] (Box 9 (Art))
  - Portrait mask of Marsden Hartley, [1923] (Box 10)
  - Self portrait in monk's costume, [1947] (Box 11 (Art))
  - "Sketches and Pornographical linoleum prints", undated (Box 20)
- Photographs, 1909-1923; Series IV; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  Series IV. Photographs contains images of Ronnebeck's sculptures and the work of others, images of the artist at work and with other people, and albums containing images dating from the war years, 1914 through 1917. There are photographs of urban and rural landscapes, architectural monuments, and soldiers.
  - Photographs of sculpture, 1919, undated; 3 (Box 12)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 12)
  - Photographs of sculpture, 1912-1923, undated; 4 (Box 13)
  - Photographs, 1909-1918, undated (Box 14)
  - Photograph albums, 1914-1917, undated; 2 (Box 14)
- Printed Materials, 1909-1948; Series V; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  Series V. Printed Materials contains art catalogs, ephemera, and clippings.
  - Printed materials, 1909-1943, undated; 6 (Box 15)
  - Printed materials, 1914-1948, undated; 6 (Box 16)
  - Printed materials, [circa 1926-1947]; 2 (Box 17)
- Other Materials, 1896-1938; Series VI; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series VI. Other Materials contains all other material in the collection by or relating to Arnold Ronnebeck. Materials include biographical information, personal papers, such as passports and medals, and childhood sketchbooks.
  - Biographical information on A. Ronnebeck, 1920, undated (Box 18)
  - Inventory of Ronnebeck material, undated (Box 18)
  - Material relating to Speer controversy, 1934-1938, undated; 4 (Box 18)
  - Medals, undated (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1921-1931, undated (Box 19)
  - Sketchbooks, 1896, undated (Box 19)